本中文字幕由谭宏涛(snl)、朱亚力(Alex)、厉致谦(colourphilosoph)、
江疆(jjgod)、杜钦(cognito)共同翻译完成，
Typo-CoLab出品，请勿用于商业目的
Type is saying things to us all the time.
字体永远在对我们诉说着什么
Typefaces express a mood,an atmosphere,
字体总是在传达某种情绪和氛围
they give words a certain coloring.
赋予词语某种“色彩”
Everywhere you look, you see typefaces.
无论你朝哪里看，你总是能看到各种字体
But there's probably one you see more than any other one, and that's Helvetica.
但其中有一种可能是你见的最多的，那就是 Helvetica
You know, there it is, and it just seems to come from nowhere.
它们存在着，仿佛原本就是环境的一部分
lt seems like air, it seems like gravity.
它们就好像是空气，或是重力
lt's hard to evaluate it,
很难恰当地评价它
it's like being asked what you think about off-white paint,
就好像有人问你该如何评价乳白色的墙漆
it's just, there.
它就是那样的...存在着
lt's hard to get your head around something that big.
你很难逃避或漠视它的存在，因为它是如此的巨大
Most people who use Helvetica use it because it's ubiquitous.
大部分人使用Helvetica 是因为它的无所不在
lt's like going to McDonalds instead of thinking about food.
就好像我们由于饥不择食，只好去麦当劳吃东西
Because it's there, it's on every street corner.
因为它就在那里，街头巷尾到处都有
So let's eat crap, because it's on the corner.
所以我们就吃垃圾吧！因为街角就有
For me, Helvetica's just this beautiful, timeless thing.
对我来说，Helvetica就是这样一个美好的、永恒的东西
And certain things shouldn't be messed with, you know?
这样美好的东西是应该好好去珍惜的，对不对？
Graphic design is the communication framework,
平面设计是信息沟通的“框架”
through which these messages, about what the world is now
它承载着各样的信息，诸如这个世界的现状
and what we should aspire to,
我们对未来的向往
it's the way they reach us.
信息就是通过这样的方式传达给我们
The designer has an enormous responsibility,
所以设计师们担负着极其重大的责任
those are the people putting their wires into our heads.
他们是那些将线路接入我们大脑的人
Now should l talk? Should l not talk?
现在我应该说吗？不应该说吗？
You want me to say something?
你希望我说点什么吗？
Say something, say nothing?
说吗，不说吗？
The life of a designer is a life of fight:
设计师的生活是战斗的生活
fight against the ugliness.
对抗丑陋的战斗
Just like a doctor fights against disease.
就好像医生对抗疾病一样
For us, the visual disease is what we have around,
对我们而言，我们的周边漫布着这种视觉的“疾病”
and what we try to do is to cure it somehow, with design.
我们所竭力要做的，就是通过设计，来治愈这种“疾病”
A good typographer always has sensitivity about the distance between the  letters.
一个好的字体排印设计师，对字母之间的距离永远有着高度的敏感
We think typography is black and white.
我们以为排印设计就是黑色加白色
Typography is really white, it's not even black.
而排印实际上是白的，而不是黑的
lt is the space between the blacks that really makes it.
因为字体是由黑色形体之间的空间来定义的
ln a sense it's like music,
这有点象音乐
it's not the notes, it's the space you put between the notes that makes the music.
音乐不是由音符，而是由音符之间的空间来定义的
For instance, we designed the corporate identity for American Airlines.
举个例子，我们曾经为美国航空设计过CI
This was done in 1966,
那是在1966年完成的
and the novelty at the time was the fact of making one word instead of two
我们进行了一个在当时来说比较新奇的设计，把两个单词合成一个
American Airlines by making AmericanAirlines all one word,
我们把 American 和 Airlines 连接成一个单词 AmericanAirlines（美国航空）
half red and half blue, just separated by the color.
一半红色，一半蓝色，仅仅用颜色来区分
What could me more American than red and blue? You know, so it's perfect.
还有比红色加蓝色更美国的吗？所以，它很完美
lt's the only airline in the last forty years that has
这是唯一的一家航空公司
not changed their identity.
50年来从未更改过它的视觉识别
All the airlines coming and going and changing...
American Airlines is still the same. There's no need to change,
所有的航空公司都在不停的变更他们的CI。
只有美国航空屹然不动。他们根本不需要修改
and how can they improve it?
他们还能怎么改进？
They got the best already: American Airlines in Helvetica.
他们已经是最好的了：使用Helvetica的"美国航空"
We always had a tendency to use very few typefaces.
我们总是倾向于使用极少数的几种字体
lt's not that we don't believe in type.
不是我们不信任字体
We believe there are not that many good typefaces.
而是我们认为好的字体实在不是很多
lf l want to be really generous there's a dozen,
如果我说的大方一点，那大概会有一打
basically l use no more than three.
但基本上我使用的不会超过3种
There are people that think that type should be expressive.
有人认为，字体应该富于表现力
They have a different point of view than mine.
那是他们的看法，我不这么看
l don't think type should be expressive at all.
我认为字体根本就不应该有表现力
l can write the word 'dog' with any typeface
我可以用任何字体来写这个“狗”字
and it doesn't have to look like a dog.
这个字并不需要看起来象一只狗
But there are people that think when they write 'dog' it should bark!
但就有人认为他们写的那个“狗”就应该汪汪叫（笑）!
What Helvetica is: it's a typeface that was generated
Helvetica 到底是什么？ 它是这样的一款字体:
by a desire of having better legibility.
它的诞生是为了满足人们对易读性的更高期盼
lt is a modern type. lt is a very clear type.
它是一种现代字体，一种非常清晰的字体
lt's good for everything, pretty much.
它可以很好地应用于几乎一切场合
You can say l love you in Helvetica.
你可以用Helvetica说“我爱你”
And you can say it with Helvetica Extra Light if you want to be really fancy.
你可以用 Helvetica 的极细体：如果你希望使你的设计非常的精致
Or you can say it in Extra Bold if it's really
intensive and passionate,
或者你可以用 Helvetica 的超黑体：如果你希望表现强烈或热情的感觉
and it might work.
非常有效
You can also say l hate you.
你还可以说"我恨你"
l can write . . . l certainly can write a few letters in Helvetica saying that . . .
我可以写...我当然还可以用 Helvetica 写几个字母，比如说..
to Washington D.C. in particular, if l can put it that way.
"我恨你，华盛顿！"（笑），如果我可以这么说的话
When Helvetica came about, we were all ready for it.
Helvetica 的出现，是我们期待已久的
lt just had all the right connotations we were looking for,
它总是能正确的表达我们所期望表达的含义
for anything that had to spell out loud and clear: modern.
适用于一切必须明确传达的现代信息
The 1950s is an interesting period in the development of graphic design.
50年代在平面设计的发展历程中是一个有趣的时期
ln that postwar period,
那是在战后
after the horror and the cataclysm of the Second World War,
在二次世界大战的恐怖和巨变之后
there's a real feeling of idealism among some designers, many perhaps,
一种理想主义的情感，在一些（也可能是很多）设计师当中产生
across the world, certainly in Europe,
然后蔓延至全世界，尤其是在欧洲
that design is part of that need to rebuild,to reconstruct,
他们认为设计本身也是需要重建和复兴的一部分
to make things more open,
让世界更开放
make them run more smoothly, be more democratic.
运行更平稳，更民主
There was this real sense of social responsibility among designers.
设计师们有着强烈的社会责任感
And this is the period when the early
experiments of the high Modernist period
这一时期，也是极端现代主义者的早期试验
start to be broken down, rationalized, codified,
开始解体、理性化、条理化的时期
you get the emergence of this so-called international typographic style
我们迎来了所谓“国际平面设计风格”
or Swiss style.
或者说“瑞士风格”
And it's Swiss designers in the 1950s who are really driving that along.
而50年代瑞士设计师们的推波助澜，更是将这种风潮推向极致
This is where Helvetica comes in.
这就是 Helvetica 产生的时代背景
Helvetica emerges in that period, in 1957,
它就诞生于那一时期，1957年
where there's felt to be a need for rational typefaces
时代呼唤一种理性的字体
which can be applied to all kinds of contemporary information,
它应当适用于各种现代的信息
whether it's sign systems or corporate identity
不管是用于标识系统，或是企业识别
and present those visual expressions of the modern world to the public
将当代世界的视觉手法呈现于公众
in an intelligible, legible way.
以一种清晰、明了的方式
So, it's underpinned, is what l'm saying
所以，我要说的是，在它背后支撑着的
by this great feeling shared by many designers of idealism.
是众多理想主义的设计师们所共有的这种伟大的情感
l'm a Modernist, you know.
我是个现代主义者，你知道的
l was trained in that period,
我就是在那个时代培养出来的
l lived in that period. l love Modernism.
我生活在那个时代，我爱现代主义
l go next week to London to see the exhibition of Modernism.
下一周我就要去伦敦，参观那里的现代主义展
l want it, you know.
我需要它，你知道
And well, that's my life.
噢，那是我的生命
l'm surrounded with furniture from that period. l can't change myself any more.
我的周围全都是那一时期的家具。我已经不能改变自己了
But if l see today designers, they use all typefaces-one day one typeface,
但看看今天的设计师们，他们什么字体都用，今天这种字体
the other day the other typeface, all in favor of a certain atmosphere,
明天那种字体，完全取决于当时的心情喜好
l'm not . . . l don't like that.
我就不是...我不喜欢这样
l'm always interested in clarity.
我永远倾向于清晰的风格
lt should be clear,
它应该是清楚的
it should be readable, it should be straightforward.
应该是可读的，也应该是直截了当的
So l started using, gradually, grids for my design,
所以渐渐的我开始在我的设计中使用网格
for my catalogues for museums.
在我为博物馆所做的一个目录设计中
l invented a grid, and within the grid
我发明了一种网格，在这种网格中
l played my game.
我可以任意发挥
But always along the lines of the grid,
但从不会脱离网格线
so that there is a certain order in it.
所以总是会有某种秩序在里面
That's why l use grids,
这便是我使用网格的原因
that's why they call me ''Gridnik.''
所以有人叫我“网格怪人”
For me, it's a tool of creating order,
对我而言，这是一种创造秩序的工具
and creating order is typography.
而所谓字体排印，就是创造秩序
l started late with the computer.
我很晚才开始使用电脑
l think it was in 1993 that l bought my first computer
大约在1993年我买了我的第一台电脑
and l learned myself and l can handle it now quite well
然后我开始自学，到现在已经能很自如的操纵它了
but not like the young people.
但还是比不上年轻人
l am slow with it and l can do it.
我可能比较慢，但是一样能完成
But l'm very much interested and
我觉得很有意思
l would have liked to have in the sixties the computer
我想如果在60年代我们有电脑就好了
because we can speed up our work, we can do it so much better,
因为这样我们的工作就可以就可以完成得更快，完成得更好
and especially all the layers you can bring into your work.
特别是当你需要在作品中使用图层的时候
We had the greatest problem in the sixties to bring two or three layers into the work.
在那个年代，在设计中使用2-3个图层是一个极为麻烦的事情
You need to do it by photograph, you did all kinds of crazy techniques
你需要求助于摄影技术，用尽一切疯狂的技巧
and working on a poster took us days.
做一张海报会花上我们好多天时间
And now within half an hour you have your ideas and you can make variations
而现在，不到一个半小时，你就可以有不同的创意，做出几个备选设计
and make a good choice.
然后选出一个最好的
You can't do better design with a computer,
计算机不能帮你做出更好的设计
but you can speed up your work enormously.
但可以极大的提升你的工作效率
Shall l begin?
我可以开始了吗？
l made these post stamps on the Stijl movement.
这是我设计的几张关于荷兰风格派运动的邮票
ln the beginning, if you see the sketches,
在开始的时候，你看看这些草图
l tried to use typefaces from van Doesburg,
one of the artists of the Stijl movement.
我原本打算采用来自 Van Doesburg 的字体，
Van Doesburg 是荷兰风格派运动的艺术家之一
Then l decided for the final designs
然而在最终稿中
not to use these typefaces because the
illustration is already from that period,
我决定放弃这些字体，因为插画本身已经表明了它的时代
and l used the most neutral typeface-Helvetica.
最后我用了最中性的一款字体——Helvetica
Helvetica was a real step from the nineteenth-century typefaces.
相对于19世纪的那些字体，Helvetica 是一个非常重要的突破
lt was a little more machined,
稍微有一点机械的味道
it was doing away with these manual details in it,
没有太多人工的痕迹
and we were impressed by that, because it was more neutral.
它给我们留下很深的印象，因为它更为“中性”
And neutralism was a word that we loved.
而中立主义，是我们喜爱的一个字眼
lt should be neutral;
它就应该是中立的
it shouldn't have a meaning in itself. lt should . . .
它本身不应该包含任何含义，它应该...
the meaning is in the content of the text, not in the typeface.
含义应该来自于文本的内容中，而非字体的表象
That's why we loved Helvetica very much.
这正是我们如此喜爱 Helvetica 的原因
l have to say that for a lot of my life
向人们解释我的职业总是要费我很多的口舌
l rather dreaded the moment of having to explain to someone...
我很害怕向别人解释我的工作
you know, you find yourself sitting next to some nice person on a plane
比如说，在飞机上，或是火车上，你遇到了一个很好的邻座
or a train and they ask you sooner or later what you do
他们总是免不了会问及你的职业
and if you say type designer, they generally look completely blank.
如果你说自己是一个字体设计师，通常他们的表情是一脸茫然
Occasionally, someone will actually know the term
不过偶尔的，会有人能真正理解这个术语
but then will say, ''l thought they were all dead.''
但接着他们会说：“我以为他们都过世了。”
Since l did some work for Microsoft in the mid-nineties on screen fonts,
从90年代中期开始，我为微软开发屏幕字体
particularly Verdana and Georgia,
主要是 Verdana 和 Georgia
l've had quite comical encounters with people who will say,
我有过好几次很搞笑的偶遇，他们会说
''Oh, you work with fonts.
“噢，你是做字体工作的
We just got this memo round the office
saying we've all got to start using something called Verdana.
我们的办公室到处都是那种备忘便签，
提醒我们准备要使用一种叫做 Verdana 的东西
Have you ever heard of it?''
你听说过这种东西吗？”
Funny conversations that never would have happened to me
thirty, forty years ago.
而在三、四十年前，我就不会遇到这样搞笑的谈话
My dad was a typographer, and although he didn't push me to follow in his footsteps
我的父亲是一个排版设计师，不过他并没有逼着我子承父业
when l left school, high school in the UK, l
had a year to fill before going to university
那时我高中毕业，在去读大学之前我有一年的空闲
and l got sent as a trainee, an unpaid trainee, intern,
于是这段时间我作为一个没有薪水的实习生
to a type foundry in the Netherlands,
去荷兰一家造字厂实习
where l spent a year learning what turned
out to be a completely obsolete trade
在那里，我花了整整一年的时间，
去学习一种后来证明完全被废弃的手艺：
of making type by hand.
手工造字
lt was a matter of cutting letters in steel, engraving them at actual size.
每天做的就是切割钢铁的字模，按实际尺寸雕刻
You know, l doubt if l ever got up quite to one letter a day at that time.
我怀疑，我那时即便竭尽全力也无法在一天内完成一个字母
So, you know, l could say that really l've made type by practically all the means
所以我可以说，我已经亲身经历了所有的造字方式
it's ever been made in the fifty, fifty-one years that l've been working.
——在我干这一行的50、51年里所有的造字方式
lt's hard to generalize about the way type designers work.
很难用一两句话说明字体设计师的工作方式
There isn't a generality of us.
我们的工作方法不尽相同
But l think that most type designers if they were sitting in this chair
但是我想从事这一行的大多数字体设计师
would essentially start in much the same way.
大体上来说都是这样开始的
l'd probably start with a lowercase h.
我通常会从一个小写的 h 开始
it tells me, first of all, whether this is a sans serif or a serif typeface.
它会告诉我们一些信息，首先，这是一个“衬线”还是“无衬线”字体
lf it were a serif face it would look like this
如果是一个“衬线字体”，它应该是这样的
here are the serifs so called, these little feet
这就是所谓的“衬线”，这些小小的“脚”
on the bottom and top of the principal strokes of the letter.
在字母主干笔画的底部和顶部
Are they heavy, are they light, what is the nature of the serif,
它是粗体吗，还是一个细体，这种衬线体有什么特性
is there a lot of thick-thin contrast in the letter form;
在外形上是否有着粗细的对比
what are the proportions of the overall height, the ascender, so-called of the h,
总体的高度比例如何，h 的“上升部”占多少
and the x-height part of it,
它的“ x-高度”占多少
Then because an h is a straight-sided letter,
然后由于 h 是一个直线边的字母
l would then do a round letter like an o along side it.
我会做一个圆形的字母，比如说一个 o，放在它旁边
l can get a sense of how the weight of the curved part of the o
relates to the straight part of the h.
我就可以直观的比较，这个 o 的曲线部分的“重量”
是否能匹配这个 h 的直线部分
And already there is a huge amount of DNA is just a couple of letterforms like that.
仅仅是这样简单的一对字母，就携带着大量决定这套字体外形的“基因”
l'd then probably do something like a lowercase p
然后我可能会做一个小写的 p
because it's half straight and half round;
因为它一半是直边，一半是圆形的
and also it has a descending stroke,
同时，它还有一个“下降笔画”
which is another vertical dimension that l
would be interested in establishing.
这是我想要确立的另外一个“垂直维度”
Then l would then build on that.
然后我就以此为依据，接着往下做
lf you've got an h you've got an awful lot of information
如果你有了一个 h，你就已经拥有了极其丰富的信息
about m, n, and u in the lower case.
足以建立这些小写的 m、n、和 u
lf you've got a p you've got q and b and d and so on.
如果你有了一个 p，就等于有了一个 q 和 b 还有 d，等等，依此类推
And then just as soon as possible l would get them into words
然后，我会尽早的把它们匹配成单词
or something that looked like words
或是让它们看起来象单词
because for me the experience of reading
something is so critical in judging it as a typeface
因为如果要评判一款字体，它的阅读体验是至关重要的
because l find that is the acid test of how a typeface performs.
我认为这是评价一款字体性能表现的“酸性测试”
One of the most characteristic and to my
mind beautiful things about Helvetica
就我而言，Helvetica 最迷人的特质之一
is these horizontal terminals, you see in the lower case a and c and e and g.
就是它水平的收尾，你可以在小写的 a、c、e 和 g 中看到
The whole structure is based on this horizontal slicing off of the terminals.
正是末端的这种水平切削决定了字体的整个结构走向
It's very hard for a designer to look at these characters and say,
一个字体设计师看到这些字符，禁不住要问自己：
how would l improve them? How would l make them any different?
我还能怎样改进它们？我还能怎样让它们有所不同？
They just seem to be exactly right.
它们看上去是那样的完美
l'm glad no one asked me to
我很庆幸没人找我去...
second-guess Helvetica
...改进 Helvetica
because l wouldn't know what to do.
因为我实在不知道该怎样做
This is the original type specimen of Helvetica
这是 Helvetica 最原始的样稿
before it was Helvetica. lt had its original name, Die Neue Haas Grotesk.
在它成为 Helvetica 之前， 它还有一个原始名称，Die Neue Haas Grotesk
The whole story of how Helvetica came into being
Helvetica 诞生的整个故事
is not entirely clear, at least to me.
并不是很清晰的，至少对我而言
lt is said, and l think it's true,
据说，不过我确信是事实
that Eduard Hoffmann, who had been the boss at Haas type foundry,
Eduard Hoffmann ，Haas 铸字厂当时的老板
wished to make a modernized version of Akzidenz Grotesk,
他想为 Akzidenz Grotesk 这款字体做一个现代的版本
which was essentially a traditional nineteenth-century German sans serif,
那是一款传统的19世纪德国无衬线字体
and his method of doing that was sort of to clean it up and so on.
他的想法是让它的外形更简炼一些...之类的
And it was of course Max Miedinger who made the drawings for Helvetica.
当然，最后是 Max Miedinger 动手绘制了 Helvetica 的图样
l received the impression from people l knew back in the sixties and seventies
我记得我在六、七十年代认识的一些人这么说过
that Hoffmann's part in this was a very much more significant one
当年 Hoffmann 在其中担负的角色其实是相当重要的
than you might just assume by reading in a textbook
并非象你在那些教科书中看到的那么简单：
that Max Miedinger was the designer of Helvetica.
——“Helvetica，由 Max Miedinger 设计...”
You can easily say this was a joint product
我们其实可以说这个项目...
of both Miedinger and my father.
...是 Miedinger 和我父亲共同完成的
Miedinger couldn't produce a typeface alone;
Miedinger 无法单独完成一个字体的设计
neither could my father.
我父亲也不行
But when both were working hard together then something good resulted.
但如果是两个人在一起共同努力，就能够有所成就
Here are the first trials of Neue Haas Grotesk,
这就是当年的第一个测试版本：Neue Haas Grotesk
which was the first name of Helvetica.
这才是 Helvetica 的原名
l knew the way things worked at Haas
我熟悉Haas 铸字厂的工作流程
and l had gradually picked up on the importance of Eduard Hoffman,
所以我逐渐发现了 Eduard Hoffmann 在其中发挥的重要作用
and his almost pathological shyness
由于他那种几乎是病态的羞怯
and the way that he would use other people's hands.
他喜欢借助他人之手来进行工作
But boy could you see his mind at work on the faces
但上帝，你仍然能从这些字体工作中看出
where he was deeply involved.
这里面浸透着他的心血
You have here a note by Eduard Hoffmann
这是他当年的一张便条
indicating all the desired corrections.
显示的都是他的修改建议
''The capital Y is too slim.
“大写 Y 太过纤细”
The capital A is also too slim.''
“大写 A 也是过细”
When you talk about the design of Haas Neue Grotesk or Helvetica,
当我们谈论 Haas Neue Grotesk 或者说 Helvetica 的设计的时候
what it's all about is the interrelationship of the negative shape
我们实际上谈论的是它们与其“负形”之间的相互关系
the figure-ground relationship,
实体与空间之间的关系
the shapes between characters and within characters,
字体内部，以及字体之间的空间形态
with the black if you like, with the inked surface.
以及黑色部分，如果你喜欢这样称呼的话；和过墨的部分
And the Swiss pay more attention to the background,
而瑞士人更关注于字体的负形
so that the counters and the space
between characters just hold the letters.
所以字谷与字形间的空间就把整个字母固定住了
l mean you can't imagine anything moving;
你看不出丝毫的“松动”
it is so firm.
它就是如此的“结实”
lt's not a letter that's bent to shape;
这不是一套弯曲成形的字体
it's a letter that lives in a powerful matrix of surrounding space.
每一个字母实际上是存在于一个强有力的矩阵所包围着的空间
lt's . . . oh it's brilliant when it's done well.
这实在是... 太出色了，当所有的一切完成之后
My father had clear ideas
我父亲对于这个字体应该呈现怎样的面貌
how the typeface should look.
有着很清晰的想法
So my father and Miedinger sat together,
and he started drawing.
所以我父亲和 Miedinger 坐在一起，然后他开始绘图
Here you have a proof of an alphabet
这里有一份字体的小样
with observations by Max Miedinger.
根据 Max Miedinger 的陈述
When Miedinger worked for Haas he did
not work as a designer.
当 Miedinger 在Haas 工作的时候，他实际的工作其实并不是一个设计师
He was actually a salesman.
他实际上是一个销售员
His job was to travel around Switzerland
他的工作就是周游瑞士
taking orders for fonts of type.
招揽字体的订单
By profession he was a graphic artist,
从专业上来说，他是一个平面设计师
but he realized that he could make more
money by selling foundry type.
但是他意识到，卖字体能让他赚更多的钱
But my father said, lf ever l have an idea of
a new typeface, l'm sure that you could design it.
但是我父亲说过，“每当我对新字体有什么想法的时候，
我都很确信你一定可以把它设计出来。”
l have here a type specimen book
我这里有一份字体样册
of both type foundries, Stempel and Haas.
是关于两家字体公司的， Stempel 和 Haas
You have to know that Haas was
controlled by the German type foundry Stempel.
你要知道，Haas  是受德国字体公司 Stempel 控制的
And in turn Stempel was also controlled by Linotype.
而之后 Stempel 又被 Linotype 收购
Now we go down to the cellar and see in
our archives where we can find Helvetica.
下面让我们到地下室去看看能否找到什么关于 Helvetica 的档案
Here we have number 24.
我们要找的是...24号
And there it is, the Helvetica drawings.
在这里，Helvetica 的画稿
The marketing director at Stempel had the
idea to give it a better name
Stempel 的市场总监希望有一个更好的名字
because Neue Haas Grotesk didn't sound very good for a
因为 Neue Haas Grotesk (意为：Haas 的新怪物)
typeface that was intended to be sold in the United States.
对于一款要销往美国的字体，这样一个名字听起来并不是很好
Stempel suggested the name of Helvetia.
Stempel 建议用 Helvetia 这个名字
This is very important: Helvetia is the Latin name of Switzerland.
这一点非常重要：Helvetia 是瑞士的拉丁语名称
My father said, That's impossible.
我父亲说，这不可能
You cannot call a typeface after the name of a country.
你不能用一个国家的名字来称呼一个字体
So he said, why don't you call it Helvetica.
所以他说，你们为什么不叫它 Helvetica（Helvetia的形容词）？
So in other words this would be the Swiss typeface.
所以，换种说法，这个字体将是“瑞士的”字体
And they agreed.
然后他们同意了
l think Helvetica was a perfect name at the time.
我认为Helvetica在当时是一个完美的名字
Swiss typography at that time also was well-known worldwide.
瑞士字体排印设计在当时也是闻名于世
So it was the best solution for Helvetica
所以 Helvetica 是这个字体命名的最佳方案
to get into the market.
它顺利进入市场
Once we'd introduced Helvetica, it really ran away.
Helvetica 一经推出，便势不可挡
lt was exactly what the designers were looking for.
它无疑是当时的设计师们期盼已久的
l mean, l don't think there's been such a hot thing since
我的意思是，它的成功是空前绝后的
as the figure-ground relationship properly executed
由于字体的正负形关系得到了良好的处理
and it was. . . oh, just a landslide waiting to
go down the mountain.
它就好像...哦，一次即将爆发的山体滑坡
And away it went.
一发而不可收
l imagine there was a time when it just felt so good
我可以想像，当时这个字体给人的感觉真是太美妙了
to take something that was old and dusty
and homemade and crappy looking
将那些陈旧、邋遢、粗糙、丑陋的字体
and replace it with Helvetica.
全部换成 Helvetica
lt just must have felt like you were scraping
the crud off of like filthy old things
就好像你把那些脏旧东西外面的污秽剥离掉
and restoring them to shining beauty. And in fact
让它们焕然一新。实际上
corporate identity in the sixties, that's what
it sort of consisted of.
六十年代的企业识别系统，大多由那些东西构成
Clients would come in and they'd have
piles of goofy old brochures from the fifties
来找你的客户往往带着成堆五十年代那些土气的企宣手册
that hide like shapes on them and goofy bad photographs.
上面有各种奇怪的形状，蠢笨难看的照片
They'd have some letterhead that would
say Amalgamated Widget on the top
他们有一些信头上可能写着 "联合制品"
in some goofy, maybe a script typeface,
above Amalgamated Widget
用着某种傻气的字体，也可能是一个手写体。在 "联合制品" 之上
it would have an engraving showing their headquarters
会有一个描绘他们在 衣阿华州 Paducah 总部形象的
in Paducah, lowa, with smokestacks belching smoke
...版画图案，旁边是冒着黑烟的烟囱
you know, and then you go to a corporate
identity consultant circa 1965, 1966,
你知道，如果在1965、1966年左右，你走进一家企业形象咨询事务所
and they would take that and lay it here
and say, Here's your current stationery,
他们会把那些东西摊在那里然后说，这是你们现在的信封信笺
and all it implies, and this is what we're proposing.
然后，这是我们提议的方案
And next to that, next to the belching smokestacks and
在它旁边，是那冒烟的烟囱
the nuptial script and the ivory paper,
在婚礼字体和象牙色纸张旁边
they'd have a crisp bright white piece of paper
是挺括而雪亮的纸张
and instead of Amalgamated Widget, founded 1 857,
再没有那些 “联合制品, 始于 1857”
it just would say Widgco, in Helvetica Medium
仅仅用 Helvetica 标准体写着 Widgco
Can you imagine how bracing and thrilling that was?
你能想像那是多么令人振奋和激动？
That must have seemed like you'd crawled through a desert
就如同你刚爬出一片沙漠
with your mouth just caked with filthy dust
满嘴都是肮脏的沙尘
and then someone is offering you a clear,
refreshing, distilled, icy glass of water
然后这时有人给你递上一杯清澈见底的、令人精神一振的，冰镇的纯水
to clear away all this horrible, kind of like, burden of history.
让你把所有的不快、历史的包袱全都抛之脑后
lt must have been just fantastic. And you
know it must have been fantastic
那绝对是妙极了，你知道那绝对是妙极了
because it was done over and over and over again.
因为这样的事会接二连三连四的发生
So this is what l'm talking about, this is Life Magazine 1 953.
这就是我前面所说的：1953年的生活杂志
One ad after another in here, that just kind of shows every
single visual bad habit that was endemic in those days.
一个又一个的广告，毫无例外的重复着那一时期特有的
视觉设计上的陋习
You've got zany hand lettering everywhere,
到处都是小丑般的手写美术字
swash typography to signify elegance,
用花体字来显示优雅
exclamation points, exclamation points,
exclamation points.
惊叹号、惊叹号、惊叹号
Cursive wedding invitation typography
down here reading,
这里用婚礼请柬的花饰字体和版式写着
''Almost everyone appreciates the best.''
"几乎每个人都会赏鉴至美。”
This was everywhere in the Fifties, this is
how everything looked in the Fifties.
这就是五十年代的视觉环境，那个时代的一切东西都这个模样
You cut to - this is after Helvetica was in
full swing - same product.
我们再看看同样的商品，这时候 Helvetica 已经开始大显身手
No people, no smiling fakery,
没有人物，没有虚伪的笑容
just a beautiful big glass of ice-cold Coke.
就是一大瓶美丽的冰镇可乐
The slogan underneath: lt's the Real Thing,
在下面的标语写着：它就这么真实
period.
句号
Coke, period.
可口可乐，句号
ln Helvetica, period.
用 Helvetica 写着，句号
Any questions? Of course not. Drink Coke, period.
有问题吗？当然没有。喝可口可乐，句号
Simple.
简单
Governments and corporations love Helvetica
政府和企业喜欢 Helvetica
because on one hand it makes them seem neutral and efficient,
因为一方面它令他们看上去中立和有效率
but also the smoothness of the letters
makes them seem almost human.
柔和的字形也让他们看起来更人性化
That is a quality they all want to convey
这一直是他们试图传达的质素
because of course they have the image they are always fighting
因为他们一直想改变他们的形象：
that they are authoritarian they're bureaucratic,
独断、官僚、
you lose yourself in them, they're oppressive.
让人失去理性、压迫
So instead, by using Helvetica
然而，改用 Helvetica
they can come off seeming more
accessible, transparent, and accountable,
就可以使他们看起来亲切、透明、可靠
which are all the buzzwords for what corporations
所有这些热门词汇都是当今的企业和政府
and governments are supposed to be today.
理应具备的形象
Now they don't have to be accessible or
accountable or transparent
现在他们可以不必真的亲切、可靠、透明
but they can look that way.
但他们可以看上去如此
Our tax forms from the lRS are in Helvetica.
我们从 IRS（美国国税局）拿到的表格用的是 Helvetica
The EPA uses it
EPA（环保署）也用它
now there's someone who wants to look
clean and official and efficient.
现代人希望显得简洁、正式、高效
Designers, and l think even readers, invest
so much of the surroundings in the typeface.
设计师们，我想甚至是读者们，为这款字体赋予了种种外在的含义
American Apparel uses Helvetica and it looks cheeky.
美国服饰 用Helvetica 显出随意
American Airlines uses it and it looks sober.
而美国航空 用 Helvetica 显出稳重
And it's not just a matter of the weight they
use and the letter spacing and the colors.
这不仅仅因为他们所使用的字重，字距，和颜色
There's something about the typeface l think
really invites this sort of open interpretation.
还因为字体本身就支持开放性的释读
l suppose you could say the typefaces are either
我认为字体可以说分为两种类型
those that are fully open to interpretation
一类支持完全开放性的解读
or merely have one association attached to them.
另一类却仅仅与一种含义相关联
A typeface made of icicles or candy canes
or something just says one thing.
一款由冰柱或棒棒糖之类玩意构成的字体只表达一种意思
And Helvetica maybe says everything.
而 Helvetica 却可以表达一切
And that's perhaps part of its appeal.
或许这就是它的魅力之一
Typography has this real poverty of terms to describe things.
文字设计中非常缺乏可用于描述字体特性的术语
Beyond x height and cap height and weight and so on.
仅有的就是 x高度，字高，字重之类
I find when Tobias and I work on projects together
当 Tobias 和我在一起合作项目时
we tend to use a lot of qualitative terms that are entirely subjective.
我们喜欢用很多很主观的词汇来描述字体的特性
Working on the typeface for Esquire years ago, I remember us saying,
在几年前为 《君子杂志》 制作字体时，我记得我们曾说
I remember my saying, No this has that Saturn 5 rocket early NASA quality.
我记得我说，不，这是土星5号时期美国航天局的感觉
lt needs to have that orange plastic Olivetti
typewriter, Roman Holiday espresso feeling.
它应该是那种橘色塑料的好利获得打字机，罗马假日浓缩咖啡的感觉
I know you got exactly what I was saying. -I did. -
我知道你完全理解我所说的。对
But it's that there's really no way to describe the qualitative parts
of a typeface without resorting to things are fully outside it.
如果不借助于外在的事物，我们就很难描述字体的特性
And we're constantly saying, You know,
this has that, it feels kind of Erik Satie;
我们一直在说，“你知道，这有点 Erik Satie（19世纪法国作曲家）的感觉
it needs to be Debussy.
它应该是德彪西那样的感觉
Or this has a kind of belt and suspenders look.
或者，这看上去有点象背带裤
lt needs to be, you know, much more elegant. . . hand-lasted shoe.
它应该，嗯，更优雅一点...手工做的鞋一样的感觉
l've been collecting these signs for a couple of years now
我已经收集这些标牌好些年了
and one of my favorites is these signs. l have a number of these.
我最喜欢的是这些标牌，这样的我有好多
This is what the street signs in New York City used to look like.
这就是纽约城街道上的标牌以前的样子
This actually functions so much more clearly
它实际上看起来更清晰
and so much more effectively than what we
see out on the street now.
比我们现在在街上看到的要更有效
The sort of classical modernist line on
现代主义的“经典理论”认为
how aware a reader should be of a typeface
一个读者对待字体的方式应该是：
is that they shouldn't be aware of it at all.
读者根本不应该意识到字体的存在
lt should be this crystal goblet
它应该像一个水晶的高脚杯
there to just hold and display and organize
只是放置，展示和组织信息的一个容器
the information. But I don't think it's really quite as simple as that.
但我想实际情况并没有那么简单
I think even if they're not consciously
我想即使他们在阅读时没有意识到字体的存在
aware of the typeface they're reading,
they'll certainly be affected by it.
他们还是会受到字体的影响
The same way that an actor that's miscast
in a role will affect someone's experience
就像安排不适当的演员在剧中演出会影响观众的观看体验
of a movie or play that they're watching.
They'll still follow the plot,
当然他们一样能看明白电影或戏剧的情节
but, you know, be less convinced or excited or affected.
但是，你知道，他们会更难于相信、激动、或感动
I think that typography is similar to that,
我认为文字设计的情形与之类似
where the designer choosing typefaces is
essentially a casting director.
设计师挑选字体实质上就像是一个导演在挑选角色
There's very little type in my world outside of work.
在我的世界里，很少有不能使用的字体
Like everybody else I'm aware of fonts
being used in my environment.
和其他人一样，我发觉字体在我们周围无处不在
You know, the standing joke that graphic
designers can't see historical movies
你知道，有人嘲笑说平面设计师不能看历史题材的影片
because the fonts are always wrong is certainly true.
因为里面的字体使用经常是错误的，这个笑话其实是真实的
lt definitely makes the world outside the office very different.
外面的世界和工作室内真的很不一样
My fiancÈ and I were trying to remember the location of a restaurant
有一次，我和未婚妻想要记住我们家附近一个饭店的位置
in our neighborhood, and she remembered it as that new place
她记的是那家饭店
that's just a couple blocks down from the dry cleaner.
...离干洗店有几个街区
I remembered it as that new place just a couple blocks down from
而我记的是
the place with the bad letter spacing out front.
它离那个字间距很糟糕的路牌有几个街区
Nobody doesn't know what Helvetica is,
没有人不知道 Helvetica 是什么
I mean, at the beginning of our careers
certainly before anybody had a PC or a Mac,
我的意思是，在我职业生涯开始的时候，当然那时候连 PC 或苹果机都还没有出现
no one knew what fonts were.
没有人知道字体是什么
I think even then people might have known what Helvetica was.
但我想即使在那时人们也知道什么是 Helvetica
The fact that it's been so heavily licensed
它能够获得如此广泛的授权
and made available through these very populist technologies
以一种如此平民化的技术形式面向大众
has kind of furthered the mythology that it's
the ultimate typeface in some way.
也说明了，在某种程度上它作为终极字体的神话还将延续下去
And even for us professionals that's hard to escape from.
即便是在我们这些专业人士圈内，也无可避免
I kind of find myself buying into the idea
我发现自己开始有些相信这个说法：
that ''Oh, the sans serif evolved for a hundred years
“哦，无衬线字体的百年演变
and the ultimate expression was Helvetica.''
其终极表现就是 Helvetica。”
And realizing, wait a minute that's not quite true, historically
然后意识到，等一下，这好像不太对，无论从历史上
or aesthetically or culturally or politically.
美学上，文化上，还是政治上都说不过去
But there's something about it that does have the feeling of finality to it,
但是它确实给人一种“无衬线字体的最终形式”的感觉
This is the conclusion of one line of reasoning with this typeface,
这是我对这款字体理解的一个总结
and perhaps everything after it is secondary in some way.
任何在它之后的东西，在某些意义上来说可能永远只能是第二
I'm obviously a typomaniac, which is an incurable, if not mortal, disease.
我绝对是一个字体狂热者，一种不治之症，如果它不是致命的
I can't explain it I just love, I just like looking at type,
我不能解释这些，我只是喜欢，我就是喜欢看着这些字体
I just get a total kick out of it. They are my friends.
我从中获得了太多的乐趣。它们是我的朋友
Other people look at bottles of wine or whatever, or girls' bottoms,
其他人喜欢看瓶中的美酒或女孩的臀部
I get kicks out of looking at type.
我从看字体中享受乐趣
lt's a little worrying I must admit, it's a very nerdish thing to do.
是有点烦人，我必须承认，这样子做是很书呆子气的
I'm very much a word person.
我是一个非常多话的人
So that's why typography for me is the obvious extension.
所以字体设计对我来说很明显是一种延伸
lt just makes my words visible.
它使我的话语变得可见
A real typeface needs rhythm, needs contrast; it comes from handwriting.
一款真正的字体需要韵律，需要对比，字体来源于于书写
That's why I can read your handwriting, and you can read mine.
这就是我可以读懂你写的字，你可以读懂我的的原因
And I'm sure our handwriting is miles away from Helvetica
我很清楚我们的书写与 Helvetica
or anything that would be considered legible.
或其他任何可以清晰辨认的字有很大的差别
But we can read it because there's a rhythm to it, there's a contrast to it.
我们可以读它是因为它富有韵律，在它其中存在着对比
Helvetica hasn't got any of that.
上述这些东西 Helvetica 丝毫没有
|Why is it fifty years later still so popular?|
（为什么它在五十年后仍旧如此流行？）
I don't know. What is bad taste ubiquitous?
我不知道。为什么糟糕的品位无处不在？
No, actually, Helvetica was a good typeface at the time.
不，实际上，Helvetica在当时是一款好的字体
lt really answered a demand.
它确实适应了当时的需求
But now it's become one of those defaults that,
但是现在它成为了一种默认选择
partly because of the proliferation of the
computer, which is now twenty years,
部分是因为电脑的发展，到现在已经20年了
the PC I mean,
我所指的是 PC
it was the default on the Apple Macintosh
and then it became the default on Windows
它在苹果机上是默认字体，然后成为 Windows 系统上的
which copied everything that Apple did, as you know.
Windows 拷贝了苹果机的一切，就像你所知道的那样
lnterface and everything else, and then they did the clone version, Arial,
从界面到其他所有的一切，然后他们制作了一个克隆版本，Arial
which is worse than Helvetica but
比 Helvetica 还烂
fills the same purpose I think. Now it's probably never going to go away
但达到了同样的目的。现在它很可能再也不会消失了
because it's ubiquitous; it's a default. lt's air,
因为它无处不在，它是默认项，它是空气
you know, it's just there. There's no choice.
你知道，它已经成为现实，让我们别无选择
You have to breathe, so you have to use Helvetica.
你必须要呼吸，所以你必须要使用 Helvetica
lt brings style with it; every typeface does.
它有自己的风格，其他字体也是如此
lt has a certain,
它有某种...
well, it's like a person, if you are slightly heavy in the middle
就像一个人，如果你腰腹比较粗
you're not going to walk around in tight T-shirts. You'd look like an idiot.
你就不会穿着紧身T恤到处走。你看上去会像个白痴
And Helvetica is heavy in the middle. So it has a certain,
Heletica 也有它的缺陷。所以它需要某种...
it needs certain space around it, needs a lot of white space;
它的周围需要留有空间，需要很多的空白
it needs very carefully to be looked at the weight gradations.
在磅数的选择上需要非常的谨慎
lt needs a lot of space sideways also.
它的两边也需要许多空间
Then it's very legible, but
然后它就变得能清晰易读，但是
very small and very tightly done and very lightly as modern designers do,
如果给它设置很小的字号，或是很紧凑的间距，
或者像现代设计师把它设置得极度纤细
it's a nightmare, a total nightmare.
那就是一场噩梦，完全是一场噩梦
I wouldn't say this if I hadn't tried it.
如果我没有尝试过，我不会这样说
Because all the letters . . . it's the whole Swiss ideology;
因为它所有的字母...完全是瑞士的理念
the guy who designed it tried to make all the letters look the same.
设计它的人想把每个字母设计成一模一样
Hello??? You know, that's called an army. That's not people.
Hello? 你知道，那叫做军队。那不是人的所为
That's people having the same fucking helmet on.
那是一群戴着一模一样的头盔的人
lt doesn't further individualism.
它不鼓励任何的个人主义
And the aim with type design always is to make it individual enough
然而字体设计的目标总是把字体变得足够的个性化
so that it's interesting,
这样它才是有趣的
but of course ninety-five percent of any
alphabet has to look like the other alphabet
当然任何字体 95% 的部分必须和其他字体看上去一样
otherwise you wouldn't be able to read it.
否则你就没法读懂它
l've never sort of woken up with a typeface coming out,
我从未睡一觉醒来然后想出一款新的字体
you know, like some people . . . l've got to do this, and they go to their,
你知道，像某些人那样...”我不得不这样做”，然后走到他们的...
whatever, their easel, and these amazing brush strokes.
随便什么，比如画板前，画出那些神奇的笔划
I don't have that urge.
我没有那种冲动
You know, I wake up and usually I want to go back to sleep.
你知道，我醒来的时候还经常想回去睡
I mean, everybody puts their history into their work.
我的意思是，每个人都在作品中体现自己的个人经历
I certainly know that when I draw something it has
我很清楚我在画东西的时候
I'm fast, I'm loud, I'm chaotic,
我很快，我很吵，我乱来一气
I'm not very rule based, even though I'm German and I love rules,
我不太按规则办事，虽然我是德国人并且我喜爱规则
I'm a Gemini, I had my birthday yesterday, so I'm all over the place essentially.
我是一个双子座的人，昨天刚过完我的生日，
所以本质上我是一个毫无章法的人
I'm always on time, but a year late, you know what I mean,
我永远守时，但那是在一年之后，你知道我的意思
but then I'm on the second.
但那时我就是分秒必争了
So I have this horrible thing, which comes out in my typefaces.
所以在我设计的字体里面会出现那些可怕的东西
They're never perfect. They always have a little edge
它们从不会是完美的。它们总有些缺陷
in the sense that I leave them alone when l get bored with them.
因为当我厌倦它们的时候我就把它们丢在一边
I know there's people who hate me, who
would never use one of my typefaces in a million years
我知道有些人恨我，他们再过一百万年也不会用我的字体
and vice versa, people who would use any typeface I design
但反过来，有些人会用我设计的每一款字体
not because it's good for them or it fits the purpose,
不是因为它们很好，或者因为它们能满足某种需求
simply because I did it.
仅仅因为是我设计了它们
I think we alI do that. Certain bands I buy every CD from them;
我认为我们都是这样的。有一个乐队，我买他们所有的CD
some of them are crap.
其中有些很烂
But I buy it because l've always bought their CDs
但我买它，因为我总是买他们的CD
lch habe sie immer gekauft,
我总是买它们（德语）
or their music.
或者他们的音乐
Why do people buy certain things? The brand rubs off on them.
为什么人们固定地购买某些东西？品牌消减了人们的选择面
And typefaces are a brand.
字体也是一个品牌
You're telling an audience, This is for you,
by using a certain typographic voice.
你用一种特定的"字体排印的声音"告诉"听众"，这是属于你们的
You'd recognize a Marlboro brand two miles away
你在2英里之外就能认出万宝路的广告牌
because they use a typeface that they only use
因为他们至始至终只用一种字体
You can buy it; I have it; anyone can, it's called Neo Contact. Anybody can buy it,
你可以购买它，我都有，任何人都可以买到，这个字体叫 Neo Contact
but Marlboro have made the typeface theirs.
万宝路把这个字体变成了他们的专有字体
You can recognize any Marlboro ad from miles away
你可以在几里之外就可以认出任何万宝路的广告
because of that stupid typeface.
就因为那个愚蠢的字体
lf they'd used Helvetica. . . Hello??? lt wouldn't quite work.
但假如他们用的是Helvetica . . . 喂？？？恐怕就不太灵了
The way something is presented will define the way you react to it.
某样东西的展示方式将影响人们对它的反应
So you can take the same message and present it in three different typefaces,
所以你可以用三种不同的字体来传达同一个信息
and the response to that, the immediate emotional response will be different.
而人们的反应——看到的那一瞬间的情感反应，也会有所不同
And the choice of typeface is the prime weapon,
而字体在这种传达之中，是一种终极武器
if you want, in that communication.
只要你想要
And I say weapon largely because with
commercial marketing and advertising,
我说字体是商业广告和市场中的武器，是因为
the way a message is dressed is going to
define our reaction to that message in the advertising.
广告中信息的传递方式将直接决定我们对它的反应
So if it says, buy these jeans, and it's a grunge font,
如果用一种垃圾风格的字体说，"买这条牛仔裤吧"
you would expect it to be some kind of ripped jeans
你一定觉得那是一条满是划痕和撕裂的裤子
or to be sold in some kind of underground clothing store.
或者是地下服饰店才会有的东西
lf you see that same message in Helvetica,
但如果相同的信息用 Helvetica 表现出来
you know, it's probably on sale at Gap.
你会觉得，那可能是一条GAP牌的牛仔裤
You know it's going to be clean, that you're
going to fit in, you're not going to stand out.
你知道那裤子会很干净，很贴身，穿上去也不显眼
All of us, I would suggest, are prompted in subliminal ways.
任何人，我认为，都是受下意识驱使的
Maybe the feeling you have when you see a particular
typographic choices used on a piece of packaging,
也许当你看到某个包装上的字体时，会心有所动：
is just, I like the look of that, that feels good, that's my kind of product.
我喜欢那个样子，感觉不错，那就是我想要的产品
But that's the type casting its secret spell.
但那正是字体的神秘咒语在发挥它的威力
ln a way, Helvetica is a club. lt's a mark of membership;
从某种角度说，Helvetica 就是一个俱乐部，一种会员资格的标记
it's a badge that says we're part of modern society,
它是一个徽章，昭示则我们是现代社会的一分子
we share the same ideals.
我们有着共同的理想
lt's well-rounded, it's not going to be damaging or dangerous.
它方圆周正，不会给人带来破坏和危险的感觉
Helvetica has almost like a perfect balance of push and pull in its letters,
Helvetica 的字母中有着一种近乎完美的收与放的平衡
and that perfect balance sort of is saying to us,
那种完美的平衡似乎在对我们说
well not sort of, it is saying to us,
很明显的，它在对我们说：
Don't worry, any of the problems you're having, or problems in the world,
别担心，你遇到的任何问题，或者说世界上的任何问题
or problems getting through the subway or finding a bathroom,
诸如如何穿过地铁，如何找到洗手间之类的问题
all those problems aren't going to spill over, they'll be contained,
所有那些问题都没什么大不了的，它们终将会被解决
and in fact maybe they don't exist.
或者实际上它们根本就不存在
What I like is if this very serious typeface
我喜欢的一点是，如果说有一个严肃的字体
tells you the do's and don'ts of street life,
告诉你在街道上该做什么，不该做什么
and it must be Helvetica at that moment.
那一定是 Helvetica
The image of Helvetica as the corporate typeface
作为公司字体的 Helvetica
made it the so-called typeface of capitalism,
给它留下了所谓"资本主义字体"的形象
which I would actually reject and say
我要站出来反对
it's the typeface of socialism
我要说，它是社会主义的字体
because it is available all over and it's
inviting dilettantes and amateurs and
因为它到处都是，很容易得到，它欢迎业余爱好者
everybody to do typography,
和所有的人，都来从事文字排印
to create their own type designs, and l think that's a good thing.
创造他们自己的字体设计，我认为这是件好事
And I think I'm right calling Helvetica the perfume of the city.
我想应该把 Helvetica 叫做城市的香气
lt's just something we don't notice usually
它是某种我们平常熟视无睹的东西
but we would miss very much if it wouldn't be there.
但一旦它消失，会让我们非常的怀念
I think it's quite amazing that a typeface can advance to such a status
我想一个字体能发展到那种地步实在是让人吃惊
in our lives
在我们的生活中
As is always the case with any style, there's a law of diminishing returns.
任何风格的东西，都有一个审美疲劳的边际效用律
The more you see it, the more the public sees it,
你看得越多，整个社会看得越多
the more the designer uses those typographic and graphic solutions,
设计师们在字体排印和平面视觉上使用得越多
the more familiar, predictable, and ultimately dull they become.
它就变得越是熟悉，平庸和极度无聊
By the time I started as a designer, it sort
of seemed there was only one trick in town,
当我开始成为一个设计师的时候，这个行业的唯一“技巧”
which was like, what can you use instead of Helvetica.
大概就是，除了Helvetica，你还能用什么？
You know, ABH, Anything But Helvetica.
你知道，A、B、H（血型），所有的东西都在用 Helvetica
And you do need lot of sans serif typefaces,
其实我们需要有很多的无衬线字体
but it seemed like Helvetica had just been used so much and overused so much
我觉得 Helvetica 被广泛地和过度的滥用了
and associated with so many big, faceless things
并且总是与如此众多巨大的、面无表情的事物关联在一起
that it had lost all its capacity even, to my eyes at least, to look nice.
它已经失去了那种令人赏心悦目的能力，至少对我而言
And by the seventies, especially in America,
在70年代，特别是美国
you start to get a reaction against,
人们开始采取行动反抗
what it seems to those designers is the conformity,
那些千篇一律的设计风格
the kind of dull blanket of sameness
那种同一化的单调乏味
that this way of designing is imposing on the world.
这种设计方法已经蔓布整个世界
So something that had come out of idealism
设计已经不再发自内心的想法
has by this time become merely routine, and there's a need for a change.
而变成了纯粹的例行公事。这种情形需要有所改变
You come into design,
当你进入设计领域的时候
at the point that you start out in history,
你也进入了历史上的一个坐标点
without knowing that you're starting out in history,
却不自知
and often you don't have a sense of what came before you and how it got there,
通常来说你并不知道之前发生的故事，也不知道为什么发展到了那一步
and you certainly don't know what's going to come after.
你也必定不知道将要发生什么
And when I walked into design as a student at Tyler School of Art,
当我作为 泰勒艺术学校的学生，进入设计领域时
what struck me was sort of two separate cultures of design.
两种截然不同的设计文化给我很大的冲击
One was the corporate culture,
一种是公司文化
and the corporate culture was the visual language of big corporations,
公司文化指的是大公司的视觉语言
and at that time they were persuasively Helvetica.
那个时候的公司文化毫无疑问地是 Helvetica
They looked alike, they looked a little fascistic to me.
它们看上去很相似，在我看来有点法西斯
They were clean, it reminded me of cleaning up your room.
它们很干净，干净得让得我想去清理自己的房间
I felt like, this was some conspiracy of my
mother's, to make me keep the house clean,
我甚至怀疑，这是我母亲的阴谋，为的是让我保持房间整洁
that all my messy room adolescent rebellion was coming back at me
我所有的有关混乱房间的青春期叛逆都回来了
in the form of Helvetica, and I had to overthrow it.
而这次是 Helvetica 版本的。 我要把它全部推翻
Hey, I got some printouts of the stuff from last night.
嘿，我昨晚拿到了一些打印输出的东西
I also was morally opposed to Helvetica,
在道义上我也要反对 Helvetica
because I viewed the big corporations that were slathered in Helvetica
因为我看到那些被 Helvetica 粉饰的大公司们
as sponsors of the Vietnam War.
成为了越南战争的资助者
So therefore, if you used Helvetica,
所以，如果你用 Helvetica
it meant that you were in favor of the Vietnam War,
那就意味着你赞同越南战争
so how could you use it?
所以你怎么能用它呢？
What looked cool to me at that point were
record album covers, Zig-Zag rolling papers,
当时最酷的东西是唱片专辑的封套，之字形的卷桶纸
the accoutrements of dope life and counterculture,
麻醉生命和反文化的装备
obviously underground newspapers and magazines, and Pushpin Studios.
显然还有地下报纸和杂志，还有图钉工作室
Pushpin Studios was the height of, at the time I was in college,
我读大学的时候，图钉工作室是最火的
everybody's ambition. To work there, to do
work that was as inspiring as their work,
所有人的愿望是，到那里去工作，做出象他们那样充满灵感的作品
because it seemed fresh and alive and witty and content-laden,
他们的作品看上去是那样的鲜活，机智，寓意丰富
aside from the fact that Seymour Chwast and Milton Glazer could really draw.
而 Seymour Chwast 和 Milton Glazer 真的很会画画
And I wanted to make work that looked like that.
我也想做出那样的作品
When I was at Tyler, I wanted to be an illustrator,
当我在泰勒艺术学校读书的时候，我想成为一个插画家
and I had a teacher named Stanislaw Zagorski.
我的老师叫 Stanislaw Zagorski
And I never knew what to do with the typography on my designs.
我从来就不知道在自己的设计中如何安排字体和排版
We would make book covers and record covers as school projects,
学校作业是设计书籍封面和唱片封套
and l'd go to the local art store, l'd go to
Sam Flax, and l'd buy Helvetica as press type,
我会去当地的艺术商店，去 Sam Flax 艺术设计商店，
购买 Helvetica 的转印字
and l'd rub it down in the corner of the album
the way I thought it was supposed to be, kind of flush left.
我把买到的字体擦印到唱片封套的角上，左对齐
And of course it would never line up
properly and thing would crackle and break
当然它们从来也排不整齐，会裂开或者破损
and it'd be terrible.
那真是可怕
And Zagorski told me to let go of the press type,
Zagorski 老师告诉我，别用转印字了
and illustrate the type.
自己画字体上去
And it hadn't dawned on me that typography could have personality
我恍然大悟，原来字体排印也可以是有个性的
the way drawing did.
就像画画一样是有个性的
I realized that type had spirit and could convey mood,
我意识到字体是有灵魂的，能够传达情绪
and that it could be your own medium,
它可以成为你自己独有的媒介
that it was its own palate, a broad palate to express all kinds of things.
它有着自己的韵味，一种能表达任何东西的能力
So I painted this cover the AlGA Annual,
我画了这期 AIGA 年报的封面
and the title of the AlGA Annual was
Graphic Design U.S.A.
这期 AIGA 年报的标题是《美国平面设计》
And I decided I would take the title literally
我决定从字面上精确地表达这个题目
and sort of analyze what Graphic Design U.S.A. was,
对美国平面设计做某种分析
so I decided what l'd do is list every state in the United States,
于是我决定把美国每一个州都列出来
and the percentage of people who used Helvetica.
加上人们使用 Helvetica 的百分比
And I didn't have any scientific evidence of knowing
what percentage of people in each state used Helvetica,
我没有科学的证据证明每一个州具体有多少人在用 Helvetica
so I decided to base it on the last Reagan election.
所以我决定基于最近一次里根总统的选举
So that the states that went for Reagan
所有支持里根的州
all had more than 50% of the people who used Helvetica.
都有超过50%的人使用 Helvetica
| lf Helvetica was the typeface of the Vietnam War,
如果说 Helvetica 是越南战争的字体
what's the typeface of this war? |
那这场战争的字体是什么？
The lraqi War?
伊拉克战争？
Helvetica.
Same time period, I mean it is, it's the same, it repeated.
相同的历史时期，我的意思是， 历史重演了
That's why we're there. Helvetica caused it.
那就是我们为什么在那里，Helvetica 导致的
And so ln the Postmodern period, designers were breaking things up.
在后现代时期，设计师们打破一切规矩
They wanted to get away from the orderly, clean, smooth surface of design
他们希望远离有序、干净、柔顺的设计
the horrible slickness of it all, as they saw it
远离他们所见的一切恐怖的匠气的东西
and produce something that had vitality.
创造出具有生命活力的作品
I myself got fairly disappointed
总的来说，对于现代主义
with Modernism in general.
我感到相当的失望
lt simply became boring.
它实在无聊透顶
lf I see a brochure now, with lots of white space
如果我现在看见一本小册子，有大量的留白
that has like six lines of Helvetica up on the top
上面有六行 Helvetica
and a little abstract logo on the bottom
下面是一个抽象的小 logo
and a picture of a businessman walking somewhere,
然后配一张商务人士走路的照片
the overall communication that says to me is,
整个东西在对我说
Do Not Read Me, because I will bore the shit out of you
不要读我，因为我会让你无聊到死
not just visually, but also in content
不只是在视觉上，而且在内容上
because the content will likely say the same as it says to me visually.
因为内容和视觉往往是一致的
I was in terrible rock bands when I was fifteen, sixteen, seventeen,
我15，16，17岁的时候参加过一些很糟糕的摇滚乐队
and I think through that experience got close to the album cover
我想正是那段经历让我接触到唱片封面设计
and essentially I went to art school because of album covers.
实际上我上艺术院校也就是因为唱片封面
I probably was the last generation who got taught doing everything by hand,
我可能是最后的一代人了，被教育要用自己的双手做一切事情
so you know, we drew 10 pt. type with a brush.
所以你知道，我们用笔刷来画出10磅的字体
ln general, I was always fairly bored, you know, looking at type books
总的来说，查阅字体手册对我来说永远是一件很无聊的事
and deciding over and over again which type to pick for a certain project.
翻来覆去的考虑，某个项目到底该选择哪种字体
lt just didn't seem a very interesting task to do.
那实在不是一件很有趣的任务
So here and there I think with the records, with the CD covers,
所以我总是想做CD封套的设计
we started to do our own type
我们开始设计自己的字体
and I think there was one instance, it was
for a Lou Reed cover,
有一次，我为 Lou Reed 设计一个封套
where this hand drawn typography resonated,
后来这个手写字体因此声名远扬
and numerous projects came out in that vein, in all sorts of directions.
无数的设计项目找上门来，什么方向的都有
You know, in a more funny direction and in a more serious direction,
有些方向比较有趣，有些则很严肃
where one time an intern carved a hand type into my skin for a lecture poster.
有一次为了做一张讲座的海报，一个实习生在我皮肤上割出了字体
The type in an instant, in a single image,
字体存在于一瞬间，在一幅独立的图象中
tells the story of its making, tells you about its process,
自述了它的诞生，它的由来
in a very elegant way, in a very fast way.
以一种非常优雅的方式，一种非常快速的方式
That typography strangely became so well
known, just within the design community
那件字体排印作品在设计圈内出人意料地出名了
of course, that some people thought that's all we do,
当然，一些人认为那就是我们的全部成就
which thankfully is not the case.
谢天谢地那并不是事实
Well, I always thought that approach of people
using only three or four typefaces very suspect.
我很怀疑那些人只用三、四种字体的做法是否正确
I think this could be interesting to do for a single project
我想如果是作为设计个案，那样做可能会很有趣
as an exercise to put up additional limitations in order to focus yourself.
作为一种设定限制的练习，让自己集中精神
But as a strategy over a lifetime
但作为一个终身的策略
I think it's akin to a writer saying,
我想就好比一个作家说
I'm only going to write in three or four words.
我打算一辈子就用这三四个字来写作
Yes, you could probably do it, but for one why would you,
是的，你可以那样做，但首先，你为什么这样做？
and for the second would it really yield an
interesting body of work over a lifetime?
第二，一辈子这么做是否真的会产生大量有趣的作品？
Designers wanted to express their subjectivity,
设计师们希望表达自己的主观看法
their own feelings about the world,
他们对这个世界的亲身感受
their sense that they had something to say through design,
他们通过设计来表达自己的感觉
through the design choices they made.
通过他们对设计的选择表达出来
And of course this caused controversy.
当然这样就招来了争议
lf you take a figure like Massimo Vignelli,
who'd been one of the Sixties' high priests,
设想一下，假如是60年代设计界的教父：Massimo Vignelli
with his company Unimark,
他的公司叫 Unimark
it's right there in the name, Unimark, the idea of a uniform kind of expression.
字面上的意思是"始终一致的表达"
When he looked at this new work,
当他面对这个新作品
this expressive, subjective, wayward,
这个充满表现力的、主观的、狂放的作品
to his way of thinking irrational new way of designing,
以及这种完全不讲理的新设计方式，他会作何感想？
lt seemed like the barbarians were not only at the gate,
——“看起来那些野蛮人不只是呆在门口，
but they'd stormed through and they'd taken over.
他们已经如暴风般夺门而入并占领了一切。”
ln the '70s, the young generation was after psychedelic type,
70年代，年轻的一代都喜欢追逐迷幻剂一样的字体
and all the junk that you could find.
什么样的垃圾你都可以弄到
And also in the '80s, with their minds completely confused
到了80年代，他们的思想完全乱做一团
by that. . . disease that was called Postmodernism,
他们被一种叫做“后现代”的病毒感染
people were just going around like
chickens without their heads,
人们像无头的鸡一样四处乱窜
by using all kinds of typefaces that came around that could say ''not modern''.
使用一切所谓"不现代"的字体
They didn't know what they were caring for,
他们不知道他们在乎什么
they only knew about what they were against.
他们只知道他们要反对什么
And what they were against was Helvetica.
他们要反对的就是 Helvetica
I had no formal training in the field,
我并没有受过正式的训练
ln my case I never learned all the things l wasn't supposed to do.
就我而言，我从不学那些我“应该”学习的知识
I just did what made sense to me.
我只学我感兴趣的东西
I was just experimenting really.
我只是在不断的尝试
So when people started getting really upset, I didn't really understand why.
所以当人们开始感到失望时，我觉得无法理解
l'd say, ''What's the big deal? What are you talking about?''
我说，这有什么大不了的？你们在说什么？
And it was many years later that somebody explained to me,
很多年以后有人对我解释了其中的原因
probably better than I can explain it now,
可能比我现在解释得更明白些
is that basically there was this group that
spent a lot of time trying to organize things,
大体上是这样，有一拨人花了很多时间组织起来
and get some kind of system going,
好不容易让某个系统运行起来
and they saw me as coming in and throwing that out the window.
然后他们看着我走进来把它扔出了窗外
Which I might have done, but it wasn't the starting point
我可能会那样做，但这不是原因
and it wasn't the plan.
我并不是有意那样做的
Only much later did I learn the terms Modernism, and this and that.
我在之后很晚才知道了“现代主义”之类的术语
Raygun Magazine was very much experimental,
Raygun 杂志 很有实验性质
it was completely experimental. Every issue we'd try a lot of things
很彻底的实验性。每一期我们都作很多尝试
and a lot of them worked,
很多尝试很奏效
and a lot of them didn't work.
也有些不太灵的
I never saw proofs so a lot of times there were just mistakes,
我从来不看印刷样稿，所以很多时候会有些错误
flat-out mistakes, that people would write long essays on
最低级的错误，人们会写长篇大论
why I did this black type on a black boot, or something.
为什么我把这个黑色的字，放在了一个黑色靴子或者别的什么上面？
No, I never saw a proof, what are you talking about?
不，我没见过印刷样稿，你们在讨论什么？
lt's very hard to do the more subjective, interpretive stuff well.
要做好那些比较主观的、诠释性的作品不是那么简单的
You know, I can teach anybody off the street
你知道，我可以教大街上的任何人
how to design a reasonable business card or newsletter.
如何设计一个像模像样的商业名片或简报
But if I bring the same group off the street and play a CD
但是如果我把同一拨人带去听一张CD
and say, ''Okay, now let's interpret that music for a cover,
然后说，"好，现在让我们为那段音乐设计一个封套"
well 9 out of 1 0 are going to be lost
十个人中有九个会感到手足无措
and are going to do something corny and expected,
他们会做出一些毫无新意的东西
and one person is going to do something amazing
但会有人做出一些令人吃惊的东西
because that music spoke to them and it sent them in some direction
因为那段音乐传达给他们一些东西，将他们引向某个方向
that nobody else could go. And that's the
area to me where it gets more interesting
每个人去的方向都不一样，但我在乎的正是这些有意思的、
and exciting, and more emotional.
激动人心的、更情绪化的地方
And that's where the best work comes from.
最好的作品就是这样来的
This is an article on the singer Bryan Ferry,
这是篇关于歌手 Bryan Ferry 的文章
and when I read the article it was very
much like so many of these others I had read,
我读起来的时候，和我以前读过的那么多文章没什么区别
and I was like, oh man, how disappointing, how boring.
我就像是，哦天，那有多让人失望，多么的无聊啊
And I went through all my fonts, which at
the time would've been hundreds and hundreds,
然后我看了看我有所的字体，现在差不多有成百上千了
uhm, well, it still is for that matter, and
恩，好吧，仍然是那个问题
didn't find one that seemed to fit my disgust and boredom with this article.
我找不到使这篇文章的看上去不那么恶心和乏味的字体
And I finally came to the bottom and there was Dingbats,
最终我在列表的最底部找到了 Dingbats
which of course now it's Zapf Dingbats so it's literally the last one.
现在的名字叫 Zapf Dingbats，所以按字母排序它是最后一个
And I was like, well it's boring and not worth reading,
然后我想，既然这篇文章如此无聊不值一读
why not do it in Zapf Dingbats?
那为什么不用Zapf Dingbats（一种装饰符号字体）来排版？
lt's a font. So it's all set in Dingbats,
这也是一个字体啊，所以就全部用 Dingbats 好了
it is the actual font, you could highlight it
and make it Helvetica or something
这就是现在的字体，你可以把它全选换成 Helvetica 或者别的什么字体
and you'd be able to read it
然后你就可以阅读了
but it really wouldn't be worthwhile, it's not very well-written.
但是它的确不值，它写得实在不是很好
Don't confuse legibility with communication.
别把易读性和信息传达混为一谈
Just because something's legible, doesn't mean it communicates
某样东西清晰易读，并不说明它能能传达信息
And more importantly doesn't mean it communicates the right thing.
更重要的是，并不意味着它传达了正确的信息
And vice-versa, something that may be difficult to initially read
反过来说，某个东西或许开始的时候很难辨识
could be sending a completely different message
但它传达了一种全然不同的信息
that is valid for where it's being used,
同时又切合主题
and that may require a little more time or the involvement of the reader.
那么，或许它就是需要读者多花点时间和心思的
But it almost seems stronger the other way,
这种方式表达的效果往往要更为强烈
if something is a very important message
and it's set in a boring, non-descript way,
如果有条非常重要的信息用一种平凡无聊的方式排出来
the message can be lost.
这条消息很可能就被人忽略了
I mean that doesn't say ''caffeinated''!
我说这一点“含咖啡因”的意思也没有！
It's just like, hello?
就像说“你好”一样没有实际含义
|Why Not?|
（为什么没有呢？）
It's just sitting there! There's nothing caffeinated about it!
它就呆在那儿，完全嗅不出咖啡因的味道来
There's nothing ''extramarital'' about that.
这个也不带一点“外遇 (extramatital)”的意思
There's no ''sunshine'' here.
这个就更没有“阳光 (sunshine)”了
That's no fun, that's not a fun sandlot.
这可多没意思，不是个有趣的地方 (sandlot 沙地)
Where's the explosion?
“爆炸”？在哪里？
This could be the first date.
这也可能是第一次约会的（“第三次约会”）
This might be close, these buses are kind of boring.
这个倒还凑合，这些灰狗巴士是挺无聊的
There's a very thin line between simple and clean and powerful,
and simple and clean and boring.
“简洁有力”和“空洞乏味”之间的界限其实很模糊
That was sort of the rise of what's referred to as grunge typography,
这就是所谓垃圾风格字体设计的兴起
and that became an all-consuming aesthetic for two, three, four, five years
并成为了二、三、四、五年内吞噬一切的“美学”
as that trend worked its way down from the masters who originated it
这种趋势从其发端的大师们开始
to anyone who sort of already had a tendency to make mistakes
一直延伸到那些时常犯错的家伙
and all of sudden found that they looked good now instead of incompetent,
他们忽然之间发现自己可以胜任了
which is how they looked the day before.
不再象以前那样白痴无能
Typography was so broken by the end of the grunge period,
垃圾时代末期的字体排印设计残破不堪
just lying there in a twisted heap,
就像置身于一堆混乱之中
all rules cast aside, no apparent way forward,
所有的规则都被抛弃了，前方看不到出路
that all those designers could perhaps do by the late nineties was to go back
所以这些设计师们在 90 年代末能做的就是回归
to return to an earlier way of designing,
回归到早期的设计方式
but with a new set of theories to support it.
但需要用一套新的理论来支持它
For us, modernism does have a more subversive side.
对我们而言，现代主义确实有着更颠覆的一面
I think that the whole image of modernism
我认为整个“现代主义”
as something that is primarily concerned with functionalism,
基本上就是“功能主义”加“实用主义”
utilitarianism, that is something that emerged much later,
后者是很晚才出现的
that is a sort of a late-modernist thing.
属于某种后期现代主义
I think the early-modernist movements,
我觉得早期的现代主义运动
like Dadaism, Futurism, Surrealism,
像达达主义、未来主义、超现实主义
all had their more subversive sides
都有着它们颠覆的一面
and their more, how do you call it,
以及……该怎么说呢
dialectical sides, so they went against something.
…更辨证的一面，所以它们都有其针对的目标
It's not that we are against that experimentation
我们并不反对那样的实验
that people like David Carson and Emigre and Fuse, that Neville Brody did.
像 David Carson、Emigre、Fuse 和 Neville Brody 所做的
We think what we do is a sort of an extension of that.
我觉得我们所做的其实是对他们的实验的一种延伸
All that hunting to the next typeface every time, it took a lot of energy,
每一次都要搜寻新的字体让我们疲惫不堪
and I can still remember as students that we were really disappointed
我还记得学生时代我们常常会很失望
because you wanted to use a certain
typeface and then you saw somebody else had used it,
因为你想用的某个字体被别人用了
and then you couldn't use it because you wanted to be original.
所以你就不能用它了，因为你想显得有原创性
And with Helvetica this whole problem is
non-existent because everybody's using Helvetica.
用 Helvetica 就根本不存在这个问题，因为人人都在用它
A lot of people see the way a young generation of
designers uses a typeface such as Helvetica
很多人觉得，新一代设计师们对 Helvetica 这类字体的使用方式
as a more superficial way, as a sort of appropriation of a style.
相当的肤浅，只是在照搬某种风格
I think we would very much disagree with that.
我想我们完全不能同意
I think all three of us grew up in the '70s
我们三个都是七十年代出生的
in the Netherlands which was dominated by the last moment of late Modernism.
当时的荷兰还在后期现代主义的“最后统治”之下
For example, the city I was born in and grew up in, Rotterdam,
比如我出生和成长的城市鹿特丹
the logotype was designed by Wim Crouwel,
标志字体是 Wim Crouwel 设计的
the stamps were designed by Crouwel,
邮票是 Crouwel 设计的
the telephone book was designed by Crouwel,
电话簿也是 Crouwel 设计的
the atlas that we used in school was designed by Crouwel.
我们学校里用的地图册还是 Crouwel 设计的
So for us it is almost like a natural mother tongue,
所以对我们来说，Helvetica 就好像是我们的母语一样
that's something really natural.
是非常自然的一件事
It's not that we ... I mean, a lot of people think you sort of study it
并非我们……我是说，很多人觉得你是从书本上看到
from books and then copy it or something, but
然后抄袭过来，但是
I would really say that it's almost in our blood.
我更愿意认为它早已流淌在我们的血液里
It's also funny because a lot of people connect Helvetica
还有一件有趣的事，很多人认为 Helvetica 有可能会导致
sometimes with the dangers of globalization and standardization.
全球化和标准化的危险
I'm not afraid for that quality at all
我一点不担心这种情况
because I'm just know that everybody can put a twist on it.
因为人人都可以调整它来适应自己的需要
I think you can put as much nationality
in the spacing of a typeface as in the typeface itself.
我认为，在字体间距中体现出的国家个性，丝毫不亚于字体本身
And I think the way people like Crouwel
use Helvetica is typically Dutch, I think,
我认为象 Crouwel 他们对 Helvetica 的使用就是典型的荷兰式的
and that's why I'm never really impressed with the argument
所以我向来对所谓
that Helvetica is a sort of global monster.
“Helvetica 是一个全球化怪物”这样的观点不以为然
I'm not one of those people who is a real typographer,
我并不是那种真正意义上的字体设计师
I don't know all the fancy words for all the letters,
不知道那些关于字母的华丽词汇
and the sort of ligatures and ascenders
and descenders and all that kind of thing.
比如“连字”啦、“上升部”、“下降部”之类的东西
I just more, sort of, react to certain things,
我只是……只是对某些东西更有感觉
and just do what I feel is right,
只是把自己感觉对味的东西做出来
so I'm never sort of a classical type guy.
所以我从来不是那种传统意义上的“字体设计师“
So I get obsessed about things, I collect things,
我为某些事物所着迷，喜欢收集一些东西，
you know, I've got so many bits and scraps
of paper, of things that you find on the street,
你看，我有这么多零碎的纸片，来自街边常见的事物
or wrappers. It's just making something
beautiful out of something very ordinary.
以及包装纸。它们让非常平常的事物变得漂亮起来
That's what I really enjoy, the ordinary things
这是我所喜欢的，平常的东西
that most people would just gloss over, I find really beautiful.
大多数人可能会一瞥而过，但是我觉得它们很漂亮
The biggest thing for me in terms of design
用设计的语言来说，我觉得最重要的是
is to get a sort of emotional response from a piece.
“于细微处获得情感上的回馈”
That's some of the best design, I think.
我觉得这是最棒的设计
I see stuff and to me, if it makes me go,
我观察周遭的事物，从中获得创作灵感
I wish I'd done that, that for me is the biggest thing, you know.
我希望我做出好的作品，这对我来说是最重要的事情
Or you just get this real whooo, kind of like, oooh, that's nice.
或者让你感到，哇，这真不错
It's all about that emotional response.
这些都是情感的回馈
One of the things I've always really wanted to design is airplane signage,
我一直很想做的一件事是为飞机设计引导标识
an identity for an airline.
以及航空公司的视觉形象
I'd love to do the uniforms, or you know,
seats and the whole thing, the trucks and
我很想设计制服，又或者是座椅等一整套的东西
that kind of thing. I think it would be brilliant.
还有卡车之类的东西。我想一定会很棒的
You know, I've done these twelve-inch sleeves for so long;
你看，我做这些十二英寸的唱片封套设计都那么久了
I want to go a little bit bigger scale now.
现在我想做些更“大号”的设计
It's that idea that something's designed to stand the test of time,
我希望能设计经得起时间考验的东西
and hopefully some of the things I'm
designing will be still being used in twenty, thirty years.
最好在二三十年后还有人使用
I'd love to think that.
我会非常开心
I got married about three years ago. I did the wedding invites,
我三年前结的婚，当时我设计了婚礼的请柬
which believe me, is just the worst job you can ever do as a graphic designer.
相信我，这是身为一个平面设计师最糟糕的工作
I've done other people's wedding invites, and I'll never do one again.
我曾做过别人的婚礼请柬，但我永远都不想再做了
It's the most stressful job I've ever had,
这是我做过压力最大的一个工作
dealing with mother in laws is just horrific. But I did ours,
和岳母打交道真的很恐怖，但我还是做了我们自己的
and on the order of service
然后在婚礼仪程卡上
I did a little credit to give thanks to Max Miedinger for Helvetica.
为感谢 Helvetica，我把  Max Miedinger  写在了致谢名单中
But my wife vetoed that; I had to take it off the invite.
但被我妻子否决了，我只好把他从名单中去掉了
But it was funny . . .
不过这蛮搞笑的…
I think I fell into the step of Helvetica when I was at DR.
我记得我开始用 Helvetica 是在 DR(设计共和国) 的时候
I always really enjoy using Helvetica
我总是很享受使用 Helvetica 的感觉
because . . .some people say they use a
different typeface because it gives a different feeling.
因为…有些人说他们要用不同的字体来表达不同的意思
And I really enjoy the challenge of making Helvetica speak in different ways.
但我却很乐意接受挑战，让 Helvetica 用不同的方式说话
It's been around for fifty years, coming up,
它到现在已经有五十年的历史了
and it's just as fresh as it was . . . obviously,
it wasn't intended to be this cool thing,
给人的感觉却还跟新的一样……当然，它不是有意设计得如此奇妙的
but it's just a beautiful font.
但它就是一个这么美好的字体
Well, we are less obsessed with Helvetica
嗯，我们现在对 Helvetica 没有
than we used to be.
以前那么着迷了
Yes, we were really obsessed with Helvetica, yet not more so much.
没错，我们对它曾经非常着迷，但现在没那么厉害了
We accepted it somehow ... We came to a
point where we accepted that it's just there.
不过我们还是能接受它的存在
We like restrictions.
我们喜欢限制
We can't operate, we can do nothing without restrictions.
没有限制我们什么也做不了
The more restrictions we have, the more，happy we are.
限制越多，我们就越开心
When we started school,
在我们读书的时候
the influences in graphic design were like Brody and Carson.
那时平面设计的潮流人物是 Brody 和 Carson 他们
It's only after that we really looked at Josef
到后来我们才真正仔细研究了 Josef Muller-Brockmann 的作品
work, and '60s Swiss Typography.
以及 60 年代的瑞士文字排印设计
When we started the office we really said
所以在我们刚开始这间工作室的时候说过
we wanted to look back,
我们希望回顾过去
to find more structured design.
找到更结构化的设计
For us it's very important to reduce the elements we use.
对我们来说，精简我们使用的元素是很重要的
When it comes to type, we will only use, if possible, one typeface,
在用到字体时，我们会尽可能地只用一种字体
or two, and if possible we will use one size.
或两种，而且只要可能我们会只用一种字号
We don't like humanistic typefaces for example,
比如我们不喜欢人文主义的字体
it must be more rational
我们选用的字体必须更具理性色彩
because otherwise it has too much expression.
否则就可能包含过多表达
We think that Helvetica contains somehow a design program.
我们觉得 Helvetica 暗含了某种设计的规范
It will lead you to a certain language also, and this is also
它会将你引至某种特定的语言
one of the secrets of the success of Helvetica
这也是Helvetica 成功的秘诀之一
that in itself it is already
就是它自身已经包含了
it has a certain style, a certain aesthetic
某种特定的风格，某种特定的美感
that you will just use it like that,
你就会这么用它
because of the typeface, because the typeface wants it like that.
因为这个字体，它本身要求这么做
You wilI do what the typeface wants you to do.
你只要听从它的指令照做就行了
If you are not a good designer, or if you are not a designer,
如果你不是个好的设计师，或者你本来就不是设计师
just use Helvetica Bold in one size,
用固定字号的 Helvetica 粗体就是了
like for a flyer. . . it looks good.
比如用在宣传单页上...它就会... 很好看
So it may very well be that when it comes to trends,
很可能，至少在平面设计的潮流上
at least in graphic design, we've reached sort of the end of history.
我们已经抵达了历史的终点
The pendulum that swings back and forth
doesn't have any more directions it can swing in.
钟摆往复运动，不会再摆向第三个方向
The final trend may simply be the completely
democratic distribution of the means of production
最终的潮流可能就是生产方式完全为大众所用
to anyone who wants it or anyone who can afford it.
每个希望能拥有的人，每个负担得起的人都能得到
You can have a music studio for a couple thousand bucks,
你花上几千块钱就能拥有一个音乐工作室
you can have a film studio for ten grand,
花上一万美元就能有一间电影工作室
you definitely can be a designer with one or two thousand dollars,
你当然也可以花上一两千美元来成为一个设计师
and have basically
而且基本上
similar tools as the people who do this for a living.
你使用的工具和那些专业的人士也不会相差太远
If all these people have the tools to make good design,
当这些人都有了好的设计工具，他们就会
they realize that it ain't that easy.
意识到到事情并不那么简单
It's not just opening a template in CorelDraw or in Powerpoint.
设计不是打开一个 Corel Draw 或 PowerPoint 模板那么简单
It's not about having the latest version of whatever program.
拥有某个软件的最新版本并不是设计
If you don't have the eye, if you don't a sense of design,
如果你没有眼力，如果你没有对设计的感觉
the program's not going to give it to you.
软件也不可能赋予你
I remember, years ago, a friend of mine
who produced radio commercials
我记得几年前，有个做电台广告的朋友
had five guys go out in the hallway of CBS Records
叫五个人到 CBS 唱片公司的走廊去
and sing the beginning of ''Round Round Get Around, I Get Around''
去唱 Beach Boys 的 “Round Round Get Around, I Get Around”
by the Beach Boys.
这首歌的开头
And they really tried, they rehearsed for a
week to get their harmonies right,
他们确实很努力，他们花了一个星期来排练，把和声练准
and they were the best vocalists who worked in that department on that floor,
而且他们是所在楼层里唱歌唱得最好的
and they loved music.
而且他们还很热爱音乐
And they went out and they sang it,
然后他们出来演唱了
and of course they were totally flat and sounded horribly...
当然他们唱得非常的糟糕....
terrible. But they'd rehearsed. And then
太糟糕了。但他们排练过了，然后
the voiceover for the commercial said,
''Now you can appreciate the Beach Boys.''
这个广告的画外音说：“现在你该知道 Beach Boys 唱得有多好了吧。”
And it's really sort of the same thing.
这和我们现在所说的其实是一样的
The closer you come to it, and the more you see it,
你越是接近它，对它看得越多
the more you appreciate it when it's terrific.
就越能够欣赏它的优秀
There are more good, young type designers
现在的优秀的年轻字体设计师越来越多了，比以往的任何时候都要多
now, by young I mean probably late
twenties, early thirties, than at any time in history.
我所说的“年轻”指的是二十年多岁三十出头的
So who knows what typefaces they will design
谁也不知道他们将设计出什么样的字体
in terms of style and so on. But they'll be good.
什么样的风格... 但他们会好起来
And to my way of thinking, that is a huge gain,
在我看来，这就是巨大的进步
a huge benefit that comes with this more
democratic, more accessible technology.
受益于这些更大众、更普及的技术
There's just something about Helvetica.
Helvetica 中就是有着某种特质
Something about the fact that people keep
saying I've come up with an improvement of Helvetica.
人们不断的说“我对 Helvetica 做了某种改进”
And it never is really good.
但这些改进从来不会讨好
You know, I wonder whether or not somehow there's
some whole undiscovered science of typography
我不知道字体设计中是不是还存在某些尚未发现的科学
that would sort of say it's not just because we're used to seeing it,
能够解释出，并非因为我们已经看惯了它 (Helvetica)
it's not just because it was associated with all these things
也并非因为它 (Helvetica) 和那些
that we consider authoritative,
...我们认为的“权威”联系在了一起
but it somehow has this kind of inherent rightness.
而是因为这个字体本身具有的一种内在的合理性
You know, the rightness of the way the lowercase a meets the curve,
比如，小写的 a 运用曲线中的合理性
the rightness of the way the G has the thing that comes down,
和大写的 G 下划的那一竖的合理性
the rightness of the way the c strokes are like that instead of that.
还有 c 的笔画是这样而不是那样
I mean, I wouldn't have believed that those
things actually could be right or wrong
我的意思是，我不认为这些合理性完全是由
as opposed to someone's tastes.
个人的欣赏品味所决定的
Yet we sort of have nearly fifty years of
history of the thing just sitting there
这个有着近50年历史的东西
daring people to fix it. And it seems to be unfixable.
在那儿轻蔑地等着我们去修正它。但它看上去就是那样的无懈可击
It's always changing, time is changing,
世界永远在变，时代在变
the appreciation of typefaces is changing very much.
对字体的欣赏也在发生很大的改变
Why you grab a certain typeface for a certain job
我们现在为某个项目选择某个字体的原因
has a different meaning than we grabbed a typeface in the fifties for a certain job.
和我们在五十年代时为某个项目选择某个字体有着完全不同的含义
You are always child of your time, and you cannot step out of that.
人永远都是时代的孩子，无法跳出你所处的时代
What we have is a climate now in which the very idea of visual communication
我们现有的风气是，视觉交流的观念
and graphic design, if we still want to call it that,
和平面设计（如果我们还愿意这么叫的话）的观念
is accepted by many more people.
已获得广泛的认可
They get it. They understand it. They're starting to see graphic communication
他们了解了，他们理解了，他们开始把图形交流
as an expression of their own identity.
视为对自己身份的一种表达
And the classic case of this is the social networking programs
一个经典的例子是，那些社交网站程序
such as MySpace, where you can customize your profile.
比如 MySpace，在那你可以定制自己的个人资料
You can change the background, you can put pictures in,
你可以修改背景，可以加入图片
you can change the typeface to anything you want,
随心所欲的更换字体
and those choices, those decisions you make,
而你所做的这些选择
become expressions of who you are. You start to care about it, in the way
就表明了你是什么样的人。你开始关心这个
you care about the clothing you're wearing as an expression of who you are,
就象跟你关心你的衣着，那也是你个人身份的表达
or your haircut or whatever,
又或是你的发型之类
or how you decorate your apartment-all of those things.
还有你如何装饰自己的房间——等等这一切
You know, we accept the idea of identity being expressed in that way,
你知道，我们接受了以这种方式表达自我的观念
through these consumer choices.
通过对消费的选择来表达自己的身份
Well, now it's happening in the sphere of visual communication
好吧，既然现在这已经在视觉交流的圈子中发生
and there's no reason as the tools become ever more sophisticated,
而且工具也在变得越来越精密
why this just won't go on developing, devoloping and developing.
它就没理由不继续发展下去，永无止境地发展下去
本中文字幕由谭宏涛(snl)、朱亚力(Alex)、厉致谦(colourphilosoph)、
江疆(jjgod)、杜钦(cognito)共同翻译完成，
Typo-CoLab出品，请勿用于商业目的